Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 1 -- Letters to Franklin 1730-1776 Mss.B.F85inventory01
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1767 November 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Parker, James. New york
    The affair at New Haven terminated by Holt having to pay Mr. Ingersoll B#48, which he has since done. If he can but hold out a year or two, expects to bring his newspaper through successfully; at present it's a hard struggle. Price of writing-paper higher, owing to the new duty, also his labors in the custom-house increased. Weyman continues in public service; his paper, a jumble of lies and truth, expressed in the vilest language.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1767 December 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Parker, James. New york
    Issue of trial of Post-Office vs. Holt. Has suffered lately with a fever and gout, but is now better. Concerning the payment of his salary in the Custom-House. The Thursday's post by way of Hartford to Boston is to be stopped; a rider from Hartford to New London will answer all purposes. Intends altering his paper to Monday; every day sees a slight increase. The new duties make a great noise on the continent, but no so much at home; the poor people complain much, and yet there is much luxury. Benny Mecom's failure to get along; expects nothing from that quarter. Assembly sitting, but ignorant what they are doing; Weyman still prints for them; thinks him an object of pity and contempt.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1767?] December 30; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Cumming, Thomas. London
    Introducing a gentleman who wishes to become librarian of the Royal Society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1767?; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Chambers, Mr
    Disappointed at not meeting Franklin at the Philadelphia Coffee House. Requests him to send letters for him, by bearer, as he is going to set out for Portsmouth next morning.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1767; L. 2p.; Franklin, William. Burlington
    Mr. B[ache] informs him that he has [given] you an exact account of his misfortunes; bills have come back protested, but his brother is bound with him for their payment. His brother becomes his surety until he can contrive to pay them. Mr. R -----s says that Mr. B. had often attempted to deceive him about his circumstances, and he was convinced, before this unlucky affair happened, that Mr. B. was not worth anything at all if his debts were paid; he is a mere fortune hunter. If Sally marries him they will both be entirely dependent on Dr. Franklin for subsistence. Asks him to burn this letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1767]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Garth, Charles. London
    Announcing Mr. Grenville's consent to give audience to the deputation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1767?]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Garth, -----. London
    Relative to despatches to be sent to the South Carolina Assembly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 3. N. in 3d P. Each 1p.; Douglas, Lord Morton James
    Relative to chimneys and lightning conductors to be placed on his house.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1767 and 1768; N.S. 1p.; The Royal society
    Notices of meetings of the Committee on Papers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1767?; A.L. 1p.; Strahan, William. London
    Asks permission to see him that evening.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1767?; A.L.S. 1p.; Strahan, William. London
    Reminds him of his appointment for the following day.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1767-68?]; A.L.S. 2p.; Vaughan, Benjamin
    Comparison between boiling and evaporation. Sends Dr. Priestley's History of Electricity.
    (First Part Missing.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 January 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Morris, Eleanor. Weatbury
    Wishing him many happy returns of his birthday (Jan.17th), which she and the children celebrated by having a plum-pudding for dinner, and drinking his health in tea. Her own health good though the weather is very severe; Henry goes every day to school. Asks him to pardon her writing as she may never live to see another of his birth-days.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 January 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Parker, James. New york
    Altered the day of his paper to Monday. The Hartford rider suppressed. Question of his pay in the Custom-House. Weyman has dropped his paper and has resigned his government work in favor of Hugh Gaine, who allows him one year's salary; his (Parker's) name was mentioned by some of the members, but it was objected that he was a Custom-House officer. Holt still avoids arrest. No hope of getting a copper of rent from Benny Mecom.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 January 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, William. Burlington
    Has only time to acknowledge his favors of Oct. 9th and Nov. 13th. Doubts whether it will be good policy to drop the superintendencies, at least until the new colonies are got into some fowardness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 January 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Johnson, Martha. Letchlade
    Just arrived at Letchlade with her brother-in-law; excepts to get into her shop in a week or so. Her son Sammy very ill. Begs Franklin's acceptance of a chesse.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 January 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Holt denies that he ever sent to Mr. Strahan for any books; begs Franklin to ask Mr. Strahan if he ever received any orders for books in Holt's handwriting.
    A.E. by Franklin. Asking Mr. Strahan to peruse this and enable him to send a proper answer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 February 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Wharton, Thomas. Philadelphia
    The horrid murders committed by Frederick Stump; account of his capture. The House improves every opportunity to urge the Governor to do his duty by bringing those wretches to the just test of the law. Prevalence of a disposition in the inhabitants of Cumberland Co. to support all persons who kill Indians; while this lawless disposition continues, there is little hope of peace with the natives. patterson's life in danger. A proposition that the Assembly shall give about £3000 to the northern tribes and the western Indians for the wiping away the blood of their warriors and relatives split at a time of peace. Their party stronger in the House than ever before; great hopes of a change of Government.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 February 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Johnson, Martha. Letchlade
    Hopes Nancy behaves herself; trusts Franklin will chide her if she doesn't. Begs him to think of poor Sammy and get him provided for if possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 February 18; L.S. 1p.; Kames, Henry Home, Lord. Edinburgh
    Has bought a house in Edinburgh; most complete in every respect, except that one of the chimneys smokes; applies to Franklin for a remedy; has been thinking lately of adopting his Philadelphia grate, as it promises to save coal. Will give him great joy to entertain Franklin.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, V, 106).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 February 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Parker, James. New york
    Acknowledging favors of Dec. 2d and 12th. A detailed account of the New Haven affair and the stoppage of the Hartford rider; this latter action has caused a general outery against him; gives Franklin a true statement of the case. Concerning his responsibility for the books he had of Hamilton and Balfour. Longs to bring Holt to a settlement before he dies. Struggles hard but cannot support himself in this very dear town.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 March 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Galloway, Joseph. Philadelphia
    State of affairs in Pennsylvania.
    Printed, for the most part, in Works (Sparks, VII, 387); (Bigelow, IV, 126).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 March 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Priestley, Joseph. Leeds
    Begging him to transmit the two enclosed copies of a paper to Dr. Kippis and Mr. Price. Preparing for the second edition of his History of Electricity; difficulties in the way; at present reading the History of Electricity, written by A. Grelett of Dantzig.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 March 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Hopkinson, Francis. Philadelphia
    Thanking Franklin for his advice and encouragement, which induced him to accept his cousin. Mr. Warrcn's, offer; the unusual success he has met with already. Sent Mr. Waring a full account of the negro school in Philadelphia. Hopes he will see the Lord Bishop in London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 March-May; Printed. N.S. 1p.; Saunders, William. et al. London
    Solicitations for his vote at an election for physician to the London Hospital, 1768
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 April 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Walker, Henry. Westbury
    Presenting his and his family's humble duties to Franklin; his mother hopes that Franklin's name will be perpetuated by the Boston branch of the family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 April 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, Charles. Barton
    In case Mr. Durden should write him concerning the Springsborough estate, begs Franklin to forward the letter to him at Sir Charles Bunbury's and to forgive the liberty of the request.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 April 11; Attested copy, 2p.; The Province of Georgia
    Ordinance appointing Benjamin Franklin its Agent in Great Britain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 April 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Parker, James. New york
    Issue of suit against Holt at New Haven. Revival of the Hartford rider. Details of the way Holt undermined a venture of his in the newspaper line. His dealings with B.Mecom. The coldest, backwardest spring ever known.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 April 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Has not had a line from Franklin since December. Wishing him a safe and speedy return home.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 April; 1p.; The Royal Society. London
    Notice of a Council meeting on April 28, 1768. Engraved N.S. J. Robertson, Chairman.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 May 8; A.L.S. 4p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques. Paris
    Acknowledging treatise on the small-pox by Mr. Dimsdale; discusses new method of treating this disease. Pays Franklin many compliments on the style of his writings in the periodicals; anxious to have these translated together with Franklin's examination, to be published in the "Ephemerides du Citoyen." Has announced the rough draft of this translation in the honorable assemblies at the house of the Marquis de Mirabaud. Sends explanation of his Chronological Chart, which Franklin was good enough to ask for. Acknowledges the Biographical Chart of Mr. Priestley. Thanks him for the strange nuts, — walnuts and hickorics. Wants to know if the liberty of the press in London or Philadelphia would permit of his printing an article on Deism, and if so, would Franklin take charge of it ?
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 May 10; A.L.S. 4p.; Du Pont de Nemours, Pierre Samuel. Paris
    Heard from Dr. Quesnay, when it was too late, of Franklin's visit to Paris; regret at not having seen him; has long known him as the savant, the mathematician and the philosopher; has taken the liberty of translating some of his papers on the affairs of the Colonies, in which he is revealed as the citizen-philosopher, occupied for the good of his brothers and the interest of humanity. Sends him two books; one a collection of Dr. Quesnay's writings, the other his own treatise, "La Physiocratie," a rC)esumC) of Dr. Quesnay's principles. Introducing the bearer, Mr. Reboul. Secretary of the Economical Society.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, V, 153).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 May 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Johnson, Martha. Letchlade
    Sorry to hear that Franklin is about to leave England; cannot leave her shop to bid him good-bye. Begs that with so much influence at his command he will do something for Sammy, as she cannot afford to apprentice him. Hopes Nancy behaves herself and makes progress in her French; would be obliged if Franklin would always address her in that tongue.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 May 10; A.L.S. 6p.; Franklin, William. Perth Amboy
    Acknowledging favors of Jan. 9, 29, Feb. 13 and March 13. M[aurice] Morgan not yet arrived. Concerning Franklin's lands in Nova Scotia and his scheme of returning home via Halifax. Goddard has not yet published Franklin's paper on Smuggling, in the Chronicle, but has printed the one relative to disputes in America 1; both much admired, the latter far more than the Farmer's Letters. Concerning the experiment of setting water on fire. Reported by Mr. Foxcroft that Franklin was to be appointed one of the Under Secretaries of State to Lord Hillsborough; doubts the truth of this, but it is much wished for. Assures his father that in spite of great provocation, his one endeavor has been to avoid family quarrels. Question of paper currency. Evil consequences of the Ministry abandoning the posts in the back country, and leaving them to the colonies to garrison. Glad that the boundary is atlast to be completed. Sent an exact account of the manufactorics carried on in his province to Lord Shelburne; therefore cannot understand Mr. Grenville's complaints. Proves by statistics that there is not wool enough in the colonies to make each person a pair of garters. Act of Assembly for supplying the King's forces. Agreeable dinner he had with Mr. Bayard, meeting there Gen. Gage and Sir Henry Moore. Has just seen that Franklin has been chosen agent for Georgia; anxious to know if he will accept it.
    1 See Ford's Bibliography of Benjamin Franklin, p. 135, No. 302.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1765 May 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Howard, Martin Jr. Newport, R.I
    Wrote to him some time past and mentioned the petition signed by a few here for a Royal Government. The pamphlet entitled "A Letter from Halifax" has involved him in a paper war and he has taken the side of the Mother Country against her ungrateful sons. Has lately published "A Defence of the Halifax Letter." His attitude has rendered him not a little obnoxious. Asks his influence of have him appointed Receiver of Stamp Duties. Party is high in Philadelphia and every measure of decency is renounced by the antagonists there. Mr. [Samuel] Ward elected Governor of Rhode Island.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 May 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    His son about to embark for London; durst not recommend him to Franklin's regard; ignorant if he will even wait on him. Nothing pleasing to write about.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 May 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Sends this with his unhappy son; leaves to Franklin's discretion how far he may be an object of his regard; nothing else to say in his favor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 May 20; Printed N. 1p.; Saunders, William. London
    Notice of the day of the election for a physician to the London Hospital.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 June 14; A.L.S. 4p.; Dalibard, Thomas François. Paris
    Acknowledging his favors of March last. Prevented by various incidents from reading Dr. Priestley's History of Electricity. Death of M. Camus of the Academy. Begs to know when Franklin intends paying Paris a visit; Dr. and Mrs. Dubourg and Mesdemoiselles Basseporte and BihC)ron are greatly desirous of seeing him before his return to America. New arrangement of the museums in the Jardin du Roi.
    Printed, in part in Hale's Franklin in France, I, 15.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 June 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Walker, Hannah. Westbury
    Thanking Franklin for his favor to her son Henry. Has been in great trouble owing to her son Johnny's eyes; after being prevented some time by her husband, finally took him to Banbury to consult a famous gentlewoman there, who takes nothing for her services, but she said it was too late to do anything. Damage done by the late heavy rains to their present abode; hopes that Franklin and Mrs. Stevenson will not disappoint them about providing them with a better dwelling; mentions one in the middle of the town, in every way suitable.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 June 16; L. 2p.; -----,-----. Versailles
    Giving an account of two incidents which recently happened in which the young Dauphin displayed good qualities and a high sense of justice. Thinks the young Prince gives promise of being a wise and just King.
    (Copy by Franklin.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 June 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Acknowledging favor of April 16, with Mr. Strahan's memorandum about Holt; unfortunate that he (Parker) has to pay for books which he never received. His son probably arrived in England; wishes he had sown his wild oats while single; hopes he will be preserved from utter ruin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 June 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Hears Franklin is about to embark for home; wishes him a good passage. Durst not ask any favors for his son, but trusts to Franklin's kindness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 July 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, F. Samuel. Deptford
    Being engaged at Deptford, has been hindered from delivering his letter, which he now sends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 July 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Falconer, Capt. Nathaniel. Off Dover
    Announcing his landing, after a passage of five weeks and three days. Franklin's family as well when he left home; will wait on Franklin with his letters as soon as he gets to London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 July 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Sends this line on the chance of Franklin not having, yet left England. Continues to rub along in the old way, but thinks he is almost at the end of his journey.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 July 20; 2p. Parchment.; George, III. New York
    Commission for deciding the boundary line between New York and New Jersey. 1 sheet, parchment.
    E. Notice that the first Meeting will be held on July 18th, 1769. Parchment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1768 August 13]; A.L.S. 1p.; Alleyne, John. Fachiney
    Returns thanks for congratulations upon his marriage and for his advice.
    In answer to Dr. Franklin's letter of Aug. 9. 1768, printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 413; Bigelow, IV, 196).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 August 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Swinton, John. Jr. Edinburgh
    Begging him to transmit the enclosed letter to Governor Franklin who was good enough to advance for him four guineas, for which he herewith sends Dr. Franklin an order.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 September 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Parker, James. New york
    Acknowledging favor of April 20. Concerning the unhappy affair of the books sent him by Franklin; how much money he has already lost through that transaction; cheated by both his kinsman and Holt, to whom at different times the books were confided; has collected all that are left; will do what he can to repair Franklin's loss.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 September 3; A.L.S. 4p.; Timothy, Peter. Charleston, S. C
    The bearer is the young man Franklin desired him to inquire about; sketches his history. Mr. Spencer happily settled, owing to Franklin's recommendation. He (Timothy) is the most unpopular man in the Province, since taking a place in the post-office at the time of the Stamp Act. Flourishing condition of South Carolina; many improvements in Charleston. Lawyers, doctors and planters grow rich, merchants do not so well. Great confusion however prevails; people in the back settlements, calling themselves regulators, are in arms and acknowledge no authority; they owe their origin to "Grenville's hellish idea of an Stamp Act."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 September 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Has not had a line from Franklin for many months; has heard nothing from his unhappy son, whether he be dead or alive; some mention of him by Franklin would have been appreciated.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 September 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Parker, James. New york
    Sends Franklin new of his son and daughter. Complains of the Nation being in debt, yet five or six commissioners are sent to Boston with a salary of £3000 sterling per annum; thinks this absurd, as they do nothing but ape their superiors in haughty bearing.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 October 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Hardly able to hold a pen, owing to gout in his right hand. Acknowledging his favor of Aug. 9, giving an account of his (Parker's) son's base behavior in attempting to get money of Mrs. Cummings; his wife died on the 7th inst., leaving a girl of three years old; hopes he may be spared until she arrives above the reach of want of a little education.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 October 17; A.L.S. 4p.; Galloway, Joseph. Philadelphia
    Affairs of Pennsylvania. Two regiments arrived in Boston. Governor Franklin attending an Indian treaty at Fort Stanwix. The retirement of Mr. Hughes to the country, disgusted with his friends and all the world.
    Printed for the most part, in Works (Sparks, VII, 416); (Bigelaw, IV, 210).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 October 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Distressed at his son's meanness and viciousness; hopes Franklin will admonish him; distressed enough in other quarters; bad attack of gout; no settlement with Holt, but thinks he wearies of his confinement.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 October 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Todd, Anthony. Gen. Post Office
    As Lord Le Despencer cannot get at his oats in time for Franklin to send them to America, herewith sends his last year's produce, having added a little more Swiss barley.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 November 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Priestley, Joseph. Leeds
    Introducing the bearer, Mr. Lee of Lincoln's Inn, who is very desirous of making his acquaintance; if Franklin will give him the places of his last work he will deliver them safely. Concerning a certain experiment in electricity which he describes, and on which he desires Franklin's opinion. Proposes to make a few experiments to refute what M. I'Epinasse has advanced in the last volume of 'Transactions,' concerning loss of force occasioned by interruptions in the electric circuit; expects to draw up another paper of original experiments for the Royal Society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 November 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Bartram, John. Philadelphia
    Peter Collinson having died, applies to Franklin as the most intimate and capable friend he has left, to take charge of a box, which he is sending to the King, at His Majesty's request some roots of arums. Expects daily to hear from some one of his correspondents how his affairs stand, through whom, now, the King's honesty will come to him, whether he must send annually more plants to the King, and how to address them. Franklin's picture still hangs by his bed to remind him of their friendship.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 November 5; A.L.S. Cha[rles] Thompson and Thompson Mifflin. 2p.; The Library Company of Philadelphia
    Enclosing two bills of exchange, respectively £50 and £100, for account of the Philadelphia Library Company; the directors desire Franklin to deduct the amount kindly advanced by him to the company, and to lay out the remainder in books agreeable to the enclosed list. Asks for his opinion on an expensive work entitled British Zoology, published lately under the inspection of the Cymmrodorion Society. (Copy.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 November 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Bache, Richard. Philadelphia
    Received from Mr. Bayard of New York two exemplifications of His Majesty's commission, appointing Franklin with Mr. Allen and several others, commissioners to settle the line between New york and New Jersey; the meeting will be held in July next; hopes Franklin will be there. Expects to make another trip to Jamica this winter; would be happy to be honored with a line from Franklin while there.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 November 10; A.L.S. John Reynell et al. 1p.; The Merchants of Philadelphia. Philadelphia
    Have forwarded a copy of the memorial to the Merchants and Manufactures of Great Britain. Earnestly request his aid to obtain the repeal of the Revenue Acts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1768 November 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Parker, James. New york